Guide to the Wheatfield and St. Elmo's Fire collection, 1970-2014 MS 645
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Wheatfield and St. Elmo's Fire collection
1970-2014
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Calvert, Craig; Mims, Connie; Grimwood, Keith; Idlet, Ezra; Russell, Bob; Hevia, Damian; Clouser, James; Bell, Vince; Wheatfield; St. Elmo's Fire
MS 645
13.5 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
0.888 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_001 (0.888 GB)
0.63 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_002 (0.63 GB)
1.31 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_003 (1.31 GB)
0.96 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_004 (0.96 GB)
0.572 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_005 (0.572 GB)
0.41 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_006 (0.41 GB)
0.556 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_007 (0.556 GB)
0.41 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_008 (0.41 GB)
2.77 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_009 (2.77 GB)
1.94 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_010 (1.94 GB)
0.959 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_011 (0.959 GB)
0.68 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_012 (0.68 GB)
3.95 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_013 (3.95GB)
2.75 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_014 (2.75 GB)
0.859 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_015 (0.859 GB)
0.62 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_016 (0.62 GB)
6.26 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_017 (6.26 GB)
20.8 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0645aip_018 (20.8 GB)
This collection consists of correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, schedules, and other items chronicling the musical history of Wheatfield and St. Elmo's Fire.
Biographical / Historical
At Lamar High School in Houston, TX in the early 1970s, two friends, Craig Calvert and Cris "Ezra" Idlet started a duo called Neat Stuff. It was short lived. Craig and Ezra went their separate ways by the end of the summer of 1972. In 1973 they added classmate Connie Mims to form a trio. Wheatfield, began playing country-tinged folk music, mainly covers, in small venues like Tanney's and Steak and Ale.
In 1974, they added Bob Russell, string bass, who they met after a trip to the Virgin Islands. The following year Wheatfield began making a name for themselves in Houston, playing at universities, like Rice and University of Houston, as well as making appearances on local TV.
By 1974, Wheatfield added another musician, Damian Hevia, drums/percussion. That year, they performed at Liberty Hall and the Kerrville Folk Festival.
1976 was the year that Wheatfield made changes to its sound and its name. They began adding electric instruments and added more of a jazz twist to their sound. After receiving a letter from an Oregon band that claimed to own the name "Wheatfield," the band changed theirs to St. Elmo's Fire. At the time, they were working with James Clouser of the Houston Ballet to score the rock ballet "Caliban." The ballet based on Shakespeare's "The Tempest" influenced their new name. The ballet premiered in May 1976 to rave reviews and later travelled to Dallas and Chicago. It even came back to Jones Hall the following year.
St. Elmo's Fire enjoyed other successes that year. Notably, they performed on the newly begun "Austin City Limits" TV show, toured in Colorado, and played at Miller Outdoor Theater alongside the first cast of "Saturday Night Live." In the fall, Bob Russell left the band and Keith Grimwood replaced him on bass and vocals.
Throughout the next year, the band continued to tour. They scored another rock ballet for Clouser, "Rasputin," which premiered in April 1977. They attended the NECCA convention in San Antonio to increase their national publicity. By the next year, they kept booking gigs across Texas and beyond as well performed at Houston's Sidewalk Symphony, Rockefeller's, and the Texas Opry House.
Despite all of this success, St. Elmo's Fire never secured a recording contract from a major music label, which limited their options for venues and TV performances. Eventually, this fact took a toll on the band. Craig Calvert left in July 1979 and was replaced by Mike Sunjka. The band disbanded later that year.
In the 1980s-1990s, St. Elmo's Fire reunited for gigs at Fitzgerald's and other places in Houston. Around 2004, Craig Calvert, Ezra Idlet, Connie Mims, and Keith Grimwood officially reunited as Wheatfield and released albums in 2004, 2008 and 2014. They play shows throughout Texas, Arkansas and Missouri.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, schedules, and other items chronicling the musical history of Wheatfield and St. Elmo's Fire. It also includes items from Craig Calvert's other collaborations: Calvert Bell, CPR, Craig Calvert and Alter Ego, Monday Night Live, Hotcakes, Murphy's In-Laws, and The Sweaters.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Craig Calvert in January 2016.
Related Materials
Please see the Rice University KTRU Radio records, UA 011.
Accruals
Additional materials are expected for this collection.
Index Terms
Subjects
Music; Folk music -- Texas -- Houston; Women
Document Types
Folk music; Folk-rock music
- Series I: Alphabetical Files
  - "Austin City Limits", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business records, 1977-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Caliban", 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Calvert Bell (photographs), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CPR (Calvert, Powell, Resnick) (photographs), 1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Entertainers Information Guild, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fliers, ca. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Lamb: The Alternative Music Magazine", 1974-04, 1976-06 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lyrics, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memorabilia, ca. 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mims, Connie, 1980s; 2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Name change research, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - NEC South Central Regional Conference, 1976-11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - News clips, 1975-2009 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Promotional materials, ca. 1977, 1999, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Rasputin", 1977 (Box 1a, Folder 1)
  - Schedules, 1976-1979 (Box 1a, Folder 2)
  - Set lists, n.d.; 2018 (Box 1a, Folder 3)
- Series II: Photographs
  - Negatives and slides, 1976-1979 (Box 1a, Folder 4)
  - Negatives by Bob Burton, 1976 (Box 1a, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1973-1980s, 2008 (Box 1a, Folder 6)
- Series III: Audio and Video
  - Sub-Series A: Video
    - "Austin City Limits" (3/4" U-matic video cassettte and digital version), 1976-02-27 (Box 2)
      Scope and Contents
      These digitized video files consist of one master copy avi and one access copy mp4.
    - "Caliban" - Dallas Ballet (DVD), 1977-09-17 (Box 2)
    - Dallas Ballet - "Caliban," "Carmina Burana," "Surprise Symphony" (VHS and digitized version), 1977-09-17 (Box 2)
    - "Green Room" show - KUHT, KPRC show (3/4" U-matic video cassette and digitized version), 1977 (Box 2)
    - St. Elmo's Fire Interviews with Keith Grimwood and Ezra Idlet (VHS and digitized version), 1978-09-07, 1978-02-13 (Box 2)
    - "Caliban" - Dallas Ballet (1/2" reel-to-reel video tape and digitized version), 1977-09-17 (Box 2)
    - "Little Ol' Show" (3/4" U-matic video cassette and digitized version), 1978-02-15 (Box 2)
    - Calvert Bell - "Little Ol' Show" (3/4" U-matic video cassette and digital version), 1979-09 (Box 2)
    - "Bermuda Triangle" (1/2" reel-to-reel video tape and digitized version), 1980 (Box 2)
    - "Bermuda Triangle" (VHS), 1980 (Box 2)
    - St. Elmo's Fire Christmas show (6 compact video cassettes and cassette adapter), 1987 (Box 2)
    - St. Elmo's Fire (DVD), n.d. (Box 2)
    - Wheatfield oral history, 2017-11-01
      These born digital video files consist of one master copy mov and one access copy located at scholarship.rice.edu.
  - Sub-Series B: Audio
    - Craig Calvert and Ezra Idlet demos (reel-to-reel audio), ca. 1973; wheatfield_01 (Box 2)
      These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s.
    - Wheatfield at the Gallows (reel-to-reel audio), 1973-11; wheatfield_02 (Box 2)
    - Wheatfield, Friday Night Session (reel-to-reel audio), 1973-11; wheatfield_03 (Box 2)
    - Wheatfield live at KPFT (reel-to-reel audio), 1974-08-01; wheatfield_04 (Box 2)
      These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Tracks include: "Last Train to Ponchitrain"; "Dead Flowers"; "Laurie's Song"; "Waxahatchie Woman"; "From the Winter"; "Beans and Beer, Again"; "He Comes for conversation"; "Flapjack Blues"; "The Lady Has No Heart"; "Open Up the Door" - Broadcast 1974-08-01
    - Sugar Hill Studios (8-track reel), 1975-05-24 (Box 2)
    - Wheatfield live at the Refectory, Houston, TX (reel-to-reel audio), 1975-01; wheatfield_05 (Box 2a)
    - St. Elmo's Fire demos (cassette tape), 1976-1979 (Box 2a)
    - St. Elmo's Fire live in Huntsville, TX (reel-to-reel audio), 1976-11-15; wheatfield_06 (Box 2a)
    - "Caliban" - Dallas Ballet (CD or DVD), 1977-09-17 (Box 2a)
    - "Caliban," acts 1-3 - Dallas Ballet, (3 reel-to-reel audio tapes), 1977-09-17; wheatfield_07; wheatfield_08; wheatfield_09 (Box 2a)
    - Boondocks live - Austin, TX - KLBJ (cassette tape), 1978-02 (Box 2a)
    - Boondocks outtakes - Austin, TX - KLBJ (cassette tape), 1978-02 (Box 2a)
    - Master demos (reel-to-reel audio), 1978; wheatfield_11 (Box 2a)
      These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Tracks include: "Anything to Make It"; "Another Twist"
    - "The Lady Has No Heart / Rainbows Shatter" (45 single), ca. 1978 (Box 2a)
    - St. Elmo's Fire live at KPRC (cassette tape), ca. 1978 (Box 2a)
    - Master demos (reel-to-reel audio), 1979; wheatfield_12 (Box 2a)
      These files are digitized master copy WAVs and access copy MP3s. Tracks include: "5th Floor Walkup"; "With a Heart"; "Black Jack."
    - Calvert Bell live at Fitzgerald's, Houston, TX (reel-to-reel audio), 1979-09-08; wheatfield_10 (Box 2a)
    - "St. Elmo's Fire: 76-79" (cassette tape), 1987 (Box 2a)
    - Wheatfield (CD), 2004-09-02 (Box 2a)
    - Live at Uncle Calvin's (CD), 2007-01-12 (Box 2a)
    - "Second Chances" (CD), 2008 (Box 2a)
    - "Oasis: Acoustic, vol. 8, no. 7" (2 CDs), 2008 (Box 2a)
    - Live at Kerrville Folk Festival (CD), 2012-05-30 (Box 2a)
    - "Big Texas Sky" (CD), 2014 (Box 2a)
    - "Oasis: Country & Roots," vol. 15, no. 2" (CD), 2015 (Box 2a)
- Series IV: Oversized Materials
  - Wheatfield scrapbook, 1972-06-1975-05 (Box 3)
  - Wheatfield scrapbook, 1975-04-1975-07 (Box 3)
  - Wheatfield and St. Elmo's Fire scrapbook, 1973-1977 (Box 4)
  - Wheatfield and St. Elmo's Fire scrapbook, 1973-12-27-1977-03 (Box 4)
  - St. Elmo's Fire scrapbook, 1977-02-25-1978-12-23 (Box 5)
  - Wheatfield scrapbook (2 CDs), 2004-05-18-2007-01-14 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook (4 CDs), 1991-07-28-2009-04-29 (Box 6)
    This scrapbook contains items from Craig Calvert's other music groups: Hotcakes, Fink's Mules, Murphy's In-Laws, CPR, and Calvert & Mims.
  - St. Elmo's Fire scrapbook, 1978-04-15-1991-06-16 (Box 7)
    This scrapbook contains items from St. Elmo's Fire, Calvert Bell, CPR, the Craig Calvert Group, Craig Calvert and Alter Ego, Alter Ego, Monday Night Live, Hotcakes, The Sweaters, and Fink's Mules.
  - St. Elmo's Fire scrapbook continued, 1977-02-25-1978-12-23 (Box 7a)
  - Wheatfield bumper sticker (3), ca. 1974 (Box 7a)
  - Wheatfield logo - Letratone sheet, ca. 1974 (Box 7a)
  - Posters, 1975-1987 (Box 7a)
  - Publicity scrapbook with leather cover, ca, 1976 (Box 7a)
  - Musical score, ca. 1977 (Box 7a)
  - Blue Wheatfield T-shirt, ca. 1975 (Box 7a)
  - Navy Caliban T-shirt, 1977 (Box 7a)
  - Navy St. Elmo's Fire T-shirt, ca. 1978 (Box 7a)
  - "Austin City Limits" handkerchief, 2000 (Box 7a)